<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tfmlax.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://tfmlax.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-08T14:59:45+00:00</updated><id>https://tfmlax.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Thibaut Lacroix&apos;s Professional website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Physicist, you should have a blog!</title><link href="https://tfmlax.github.io/blog/2024/physicists-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physicist, you should have a blog!"/><published>2024-11-03T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tfmlax.github.io/blog/2024/physicists-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tfmlax.github.io/blog/2024/physicists-blog/"><![CDATA[<p>Communication with our fellow researchers is at the centre of our work as (theoretical) physicists. This communication takes many forms: talks and posters at conferences, seminars, preprints on arXiv, and paper published in journals. Yet, these channels for exchanges with our colleagues are only for the finished version of our work and the ‘important’ results.</p> <p>For the small interesting results from an unfinished project, the puzzling observations made with (or about) a numerical method, or the inconclusive approach to a problem, there is a single mean of communication: the coffee break. The details, the observations, or the tiny trick that didn’t make it to the supplementary materials of a paper are discussed after the presentation. That’s why it is often said that the most important part of a conference is the coffe break. Sure, these `little’ things are not worth a paper. You could put them on the arXiv, but you would have to write them as formally as an actual paper. As a consequence, all this valuable scientific information is simply not shared.</p> <p>I believe that this is a shame for the advancement of research and, fortunately, there exist a simple solution: You should have a blog! Not a blog on which you commit yourself to write an entertaining/insighful/witty article each week. But rather a place, on the web, accessible to all, where you would write down – in an informal manner if you wish – the following things:</p> <ul> <li>the failed but interesting attemp at solving a problem</li> <li>the interesting observations on the stability/limitations/etc. of a numerical methods</li> <li>the benchmark that you’ve made</li> <li>this little but extremely helpful trick that you haven’t seen properly written down anywhere</li> <li>anything that you know a few fellow reserachers somewhere might find interesting or useful That is to say, everything that doesn’t belong to a paper but is scientifically interesting.</li> </ul> <p>The humanities and social sciences have <a href="https://hypotheses.org/">Hypotheses</a> a platform that allow you to create a research blog with an ISSN and individual DOI for each blog post (based on Wordpress and it even supports LaTeX!) - making them easily citable. This is great! Unfortunately, we don’t have anything similar for the natural sciences as far as I know.</p> <p>However, at a time where publishing something online as never been easier I really wish every physicist had a blog. This would allow knowledge to be shared more efficiently, possibly foster cooperation, make science more reproducible. Science is a big conversation, and we should dare to use all the tools we have to communicate.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic-life"/><category term="blog,"/><category term="communication,"/><category term="peer-review"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the 21st century, we should not rely solely on research papers to share scientifically valuable information]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physics in a Second Language when French is Your First One</title><link href="https://tfmlax.github.io/blog/2021/physics-english/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physics in a Second Language when French is Your First One"/><published>2021-08-30T15:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-30T15:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tfmlax.github.io/blog/2021/physics-english</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tfmlax.github.io/blog/2021/physics-english/"><![CDATA[<p>In this <a href="https://www.symmetrymagazine.org/article/physics-in-a-second-language">Symmetry article</a> physicists and astronomers whose mother tongue isn’t English are interviewed. The article covers many topics from learning physics in English to having an accent, and at the very beginning the difficulty to find scientific words in one’s mother tongue is mentioned. This difficulty can have two different origin: (1) you simply don’t know the corresponding word, (2) this physics concept doesn’t have a word in your mother tongue. I find that it’s the opposite for me, it’s easier to find scientific words in French than in English.</p> <p>My mother tongue is French, I did my undergrad and master in France and now I’m doing my PhD in Scotland with British supervisors. Hence, I’ve learned Physics primarily in French and marginally in English (through some textbooks, internships abroad, courses taught in English and - of course - papers). Now that I’m doing research and teaching only in English, I’ve realised that I’m lacking some words that exist in my mother tongue but seems to either not exist in English or not being commonly use. I’m making the hypothesis that French is more fine-grained than English when it comes to physics<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. For example, when speaking of a lens in geometrical optics,<em>“point focal image”</em> and <em>“point focal objet”</em> are both just ‘focal point’. It may seem like a small - maybe useless - difference but making this distinction really helps you grasp more easily how a lens or more generally an optical device work. Even though the word ‘angular frequency’ for \(2\pi\times\) frequency exists, most of the time we just say ‘frequency’ when speaking about angular frequency. This happens so often that I found myself confused on a couple of occasions when I wanted to compute a period - I would initially simply take the inverse of the angular frequency. In French, angular frequency has a distinct name from the frequency but that still has the connotation of rhythm: <em>pulsation</em>. A last example, there is no term in English making the difference between a system that doesn’t exchange anything with its environment and a system that exchanges energy but doesn’t exchange matter. Both are called a ‘closed system’. Whereas in your first year of undergrad in France, you learn that the former is an ‘isolated system’ (<em>système isolé</em>) and the latter is a ‘closed system’ (<em>système fermé</em>). Beware of confusing one with the other in the Hexagon, you would be graded a zero mark! Of course, physicists trained in English aren’t worse than French physicists because they have (or use) less words. It might even be the opposite. I think that being taught physics with more words makes a student learn how to solve the kind of well-posed problems one encounters in undergrad more easily than their English-speaking counterparts because they have more specialised tools in their toolbox, if I can use this analogy. It also means that they can get away without clearly understanding the (sometimes subtle) differences between two concepts that have justified giving them different names. Whereas the students learning physics in English will have to do the effort to understand the nuance if they want to pass their exams.</p> <p>Another thing that I’ve noticed - which is more anecdotal but amusing - is that some laws or principles don’t have the same name in both languages. Most of the time it’s because there are both an English-speaking and a French-speaking discoverer. For example, when I was in high school and in undergrad the laws of refraction and reflection of light were called <em>“lois de Descartes”</em><sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> whereas in English the former is called ‘Snell’s law’ and the latter doesn’t have a name. Here is another example, during my first year of PhD I was at a journal club where a paper about quantum thermodynamics was presented. A thermodynamic cycle that I’ve never heard of is at some point presented, it’s called the ‘Otto cycle’. But, when the details of the cycle are explained I’m starting to get confused - it looks exactly the same as the most famous four strokes cycle, the <em>“cycle de Beau de Rochas”</em>! Having a quick look at Wikipedia to make sure that I’m not completely wrong about undergrad physics, I then discovered that (again) English and French names differ.</p> <p>I could keep giving example of differences between physics<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> in English and in French but I think that the main point of this article is that doing research and teaching physics in a language different from the one you have used to learn it forces you to really understand the concepts you are using (and can give rise to funny misunderstandings).</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>I happen to know that a similar thing is true for medicine in French that is more detailed that medicine in English when it comes to describing physiological observations. For example there are more subdivisions of the kind of murmurs you can hear in a stethoscope in French and the different nuances of shape of a cell have different names in French. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>At some point it changed and they are now called <em>“lois de Snell-Descartes”</em>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Or math, did you know that the <em>“théorème de Thales”</em> and ‘Thales’ theorem’ are completely different theorems? <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic-life"/><category term="language,"/><category term="english"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this Symmetry article physicists and astronomers whose mother tongue isn’t English are interviewed. The article covers many topics from learning physics in English to having an accent, and at the very beginning the difficulty to find scientific words in one’s mother tongue is mentioned. This difficulty can have two different origin: (1) you simply don’t know the corresponding word, (2) this physics concept doesn’t have a word in your mother tongue. I find that it’s the opposite for me, it’s easier to find scientific words in French than in English.]]></summary></entry></feed>